<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-11-20T16:08:04-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Andrew Lilja</title><subtitle>Andrew is a user experience designer and human factors engineer based in Minneapolis.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Medical Device Human Factors</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/work/medical-devices/2019/11/19/medical-devices.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Medical Device Human Factors" /><published>2019-11-19T10:22:34-06:00</published><updated>2019-11-19T10:22:34-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/work/medical-devices/2019/11/19/medical-devices</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/work/medical-devices/2019/11/19/medical-devices.html">&lt;p&gt;Since 2015, I’ve been working in medical devices. This highly regulated industry requires a broad range of skills and activities for UX professionals, typically culminating in a submission document to the FDA and follow-up audits to defend claims and design decisions. It is essential that all UI decisions can be proven to reduce harm and make the system easier to use — any decision made without evidence is heavily scrutinized and may result in the regulatory bodies rejecting your product. All data must be recorded, all choices documented, and all UI designs rationalized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern medical devices are incredibly powerful and complex — a pacemaker can tell the difference between a dangerous heart rate and the normal change in rate associated with exercise and respond accordingly, for example — but with these benefits come the risk of harm to both patients and clinician. An essential part of the design process is testing to ensure that the tools built are not only effective and easy to use, but easy to use &lt;em&gt;safely&lt;/em&gt; and hard to cause harm with. This is done in two phases: first, the &lt;em&gt;formative&lt;/em&gt; process, where the initial design is created, tested, and iterated on; second, the &lt;em&gt;summative&lt;/em&gt;, where you do rigorous testing to demonstrate to a regulatory body (like the FDA in the USA or TUV in Europe) that your design is safe and all potential sources of harm have been minimized as much as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like to think of the two processes as &lt;em&gt;designing what the users need&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;proving to regulatory bodies you made it safe.&lt;/em&gt; I have been extensively involved in both.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Since 2015, I’ve been working in medical devices. This highly regulated industry requires a broad range of skills and activities for UX professionals, typically culminating in a submission document to the FDA and follow-up audits to defend claims and design decisions. It is essential that all UI decisions can be proven to reduce harm and make the system easier to use — any decision made without evidence is heavily scrutinized and may result in the regulatory bodies rejecting your product. All data must be recorded, all choices documented, and all UI designs rationalized.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Patient-Facing UI Development</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/work/medical-devices/2019/11/18/patient-facing-ui.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Patient-Facing UI Development" /><published>2019-11-18T10:22:34-06:00</published><updated>2019-11-18T10:22:34-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/work/medical-devices/2019/11/18/patient-facing-ui</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/work/medical-devices/2019/11/18/patient-facing-ui.html">&lt;p&gt;A large medical device manufacturer provides a tool that allows patients to control their own therapy via a small hand-held controller. I was responsible for designing and testing the new touchscreen-based software on the replacement controller in the formative phase. The nature of the patient population required not just a highly specialized design, but uniquely rigorous testing to meet their wide range of needs. This took place in several sites in the United States and Europe with more than 50 patients over the course of two years, resulting in a final product that fits both the business and customer needs: a future-proofed platform that can be updated and allows patients to have necessary, extensive, and clinician-customizable control over their therapy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the design work was done, I needed to hand the project over to another employee. They needed to be brought up to speed about the steps the project had taken, why decisions had been made, and develop a deep enough understanding of the system and its design legacy that they could take it through validation testing. I worked with this employee to educate and train them on the product and create a document that could be passed to new employees to bring them up to speed quickly and efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project required collaboration between software developers, other designers, project managers, safety engineers, system engineers, management, legal, and regulatory — as well as cooperating with other human factor engineers working on projects that ours leveraged from, like hardware development or software design libraries.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A large medical device manufacturer provides a tool that allows patients to control their own therapy via a small hand-held controller. I was responsible for designing and testing the new touchscreen-based software on the replacement controller in the formative phase. The nature of the patient population required not just a highly specialized design, but uniquely rigorous testing to meet their wide range of needs. This took place in several sites in the United States and Europe with more than 50 patients over the course of two years, resulting in a final product that fits both the business and customer needs: a future-proofed platform that can be updated and allows patients to have necessary, extensive, and clinician-customizable control over their therapy.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Summative Studies</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/work/medical-devices/2019/11/17/summative-studies.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Summative Studies" /><published>2019-11-17T10:22:34-06:00</published><updated>2019-11-17T10:22:34-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/work/medical-devices/2019/11/17/summative-studies</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/work/medical-devices/2019/11/17/summative-studies.html">&lt;p&gt;A large medical device manufacturer found itself needing to replace a tool used to test and program lifesaving implantable devices. The new tool needed to be familiar enough that users with more than 20 years of experience could transition easily and forward-looking so new new features and technologies in future devices could be easily integrated. The original tool was a custom-built hardware solution that had reached end of life and was no longer being manufactured. I was brought in after the system had been developed to design, write, and execute its highly accelerated summative testing. Normal validation studies&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:validation&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:validation&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; take place over months or years — I was tasked with running six in 16 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to write a good test script, I had to quickly and fully learn what the tool could do across a range of devices. I had to know what a user would do and why, what kind of mistakes they might make and how they could solve them, and what patient conditions could cause the user to make different choices than expected. Each test brought with it new products and features, requiring me to learn in-depth knowledge for every test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, I had to develop, write, and edit a testing protocol that would allow us to observe use of the system in a simulated environment, matching the users’ expected flow and routine&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:implant&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:implant&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. When the scripts were finished, I developed the simulations we used, recruited, scheduled, and arranged travel for our participants, executed the test protocols, and worked with a small team to write our test results for submission to the regulatory bodies. To do this effectively, I learned how the implants themselves worked, all elements of the software, and even the physiology of the organ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nature of the project meant that incredibly rigorous testing was required across a huge range of users. We performed dry runs (that is — tests of our &lt;em&gt;protocol&lt;/em&gt; to make sure it was testing what we needed it to) with 20 participants, and performed the actual validation testing with more than 150 real-world users. The product was released in 2019, and the regulatory agency required no changes to our work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:validation&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Validation testing is just one way to perform a summative. There are many methods that can be used for the summative stage of the process, like demonstrating similarity of the current product to an existing one. For a brand-new tool with nothing to compare against, everything must be tested. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:validation&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:implant&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For example, if we were testing the implant of the device, we needed to make sure that all steps of our testing matched exactly what the user would normally do in the field. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:implant&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A large medical device manufacturer found itself needing to replace a tool used to test and program lifesaving implantable devices. The new tool needed to be familiar enough that users with more than 20 years of experience could transition easily and forward-looking so new new features and technologies in future devices could be easily integrated. The original tool was a custom-built hardware solution that had reached end of life and was no longer being manufactured. I was brought in after the system had been developed to design, write, and execute its highly accelerated summative testing. Normal validation studies1 take place over months or years — I was tasked with running six in 16 months. Validation testing is just one way to perform a summative. There are many methods that can be used for the summative stage of the process, like demonstrating similarity of the current product to an existing one. For a brand-new tool with nothing to compare against, everything must be tested. &amp;#8617;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Medical Technical Writing</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/work/medical-devices/2019/11/16/medical-technical.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Medical Technical Writing" /><published>2019-11-16T10:22:34-06:00</published><updated>2019-11-16T10:22:34-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/work/medical-devices/2019/11/16/medical-technical</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/work/medical-devices/2019/11/16/medical-technical.html">&lt;p&gt;If you can’t explain it to a five-year-old, you don’t really understand something. The acid test of this is technical writing, where one must clearly and effectively communicate how a system works to an audience with an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nngroup.com/articles/computer-skill-levels/&quot;&gt;incredible range of proficiency and knowledge&lt;/a&gt;. I was brought in to write the system usage and implant instructions for a startup’s new medical device. This involved explaining how the system worked for both clinicians and patients, and how to safely implant and maintain it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">If you can’t explain it to a five-year-old, you don’t really understand something. The acid test of this is technical writing, where one must clearly and effectively communicate how a system works to an audience with an incredible range of proficiency and knowledge. I was brought in to write the system usage and implant instructions for a startup’s new medical device. This involved explaining how the system worked for both clinicians and patients, and how to safely implant and maintain it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Existing Tool Project</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/work/medical-devices/2019/11/16/existing-tool.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Existing Tool Project" /><published>2019-11-16T10:22:34-06:00</published><updated>2019-11-16T10:22:34-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/work/medical-devices/2019/11/16/existing-tool</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/work/medical-devices/2019/11/16/existing-tool.html">&lt;p&gt;A large medical device manufacturer purchased a smaller company and wanted to incorporate their product line into their new software and hardware platform. This involved taking existing software running on very old hardware and updating it for a modern touchscreen interface and the new hardware — and in order to do this correctly, we needed to understand the current limitations and problems and how well our new tool solved them. I am running a number of formative studies for fact-finding and prototype testing, presented the results to the larger project team, argued for the best design, and compromised with design and development constraints to successfully integrate the product into the existing platform.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A large medical device manufacturer purchased a smaller company and wanted to incorporate their product line into their new software and hardware platform. This involved taking existing software running on very old hardware and updating it for a modern touchscreen interface and the new hardware — and in order to do this correctly, we needed to understand the current limitations and problems and how well our new tool solved them. I am running a number of formative studies for fact-finding and prototype testing, presented the results to the larger project team, argued for the best design, and compromised with design and development constraints to successfully integrate the product into the existing platform.</summary></entry></feed>